Guide to the Moritz Geiger Papers, 1941-1969
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Moritz Geiger Papers
1941-1969
Geiger, Moritz, 1880-1937
1.5 cubic feet (5 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Typescripts of and correspondence pertaining to an English translation of Geiger's writings on aesthetics.
Biographical Note
Born in Frankfurt, Germany, in 1880, Moritz Geiger was the son of Alfred and Adelheid Geiger and a nephew of Abraham Geiger, the founder of Reform Judaism. Geiger studied philosophy, mathematics, and other subjects, earning his Ph.D. in philosophy from the University of Munich in 1904. He then taught as a professor at the universities of Munich and Goettingen. An associate of Edumund Husserl, Geiger was one of the leading early proponents of the philosophical movement known as Realistic Phenomenology. His major contribution to that movement was the application of Husserl's objective "eidetical" method to aesthetics. With the rise of Nazism, Geiger left Germany in 1933 and moved to the United States. That year he accepted a position as Professor of Philosophy at Vassar College. He began taching in 1934 and later served as chair of the Philosphy Department. In 1935 he was named the James M. Taylor Professor of Philosophy. Active in the Vassar community, Geiger delivered lectures to faculty, students, and alumnae on topics ranging from threats to cultural values to the problem of anti-intellectualism. In 1918 Geiger married Elizabeth Muhl, an art historian and sculptor who also taught at Vassar. After a brief illness, Moritz Geiger died on September 9, 1937.
Scope and Content Note
This collection includes correspondence pertaining to the editing, translation into English, and publication of The Significance of Art: Foundations of an Aestheics of Value, a collection of Geiger's writings on aesthetics. Also included are four copies of the typescript of that collection.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the regulations of the
Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library without any additional restrictions.
Subject Headings
Names:
Berger, Klaus, 1901-; Greene, Theodore Meyer, 1897-1969; MacCracken, H. N. (Henry Noble), 1880-1970; Panofsky, Erwin, 1892-1968; Smith, Datus Clifford, 1907-
Subjects:
Aesthetics; Phenomenology; Phenomenology and art
VCL Categories
Philosophers and Philosophy; Vassar College
Encoding Information
Encoded by Mark Seidl, November 2011.
Acquisition Information
For the bulk of the collection, original acquisition date unknown. One copy of the typescript of The Significance of Art: Foundations of an Aestheics of Value was acquired as a gift from Emory University in July 2008.
Series List
- Series I. Correspondence, 1941-1969; bulk 1941-1945; (Folders 1.1-1.20)
  Correspondence pertaining to the editing, translation into English, and publication of Geiger's The Significance of Art: Foundations of an Aestheics of Value. Correspondents include Klaus Berger, editor of Geiger's writings in German, Vassar College president Henry Noble MacCracken, philosopher Theodore M. Greene, and publisher Datus Clifford Smith.
- Series II. Typescripts, circa 1944; (Boxes 2-5)
  This series consists of four copies of the typescript of The Significance of Art. On two of these copies appear handwritten editorial notes.
Container List
- Series I. Correspondence
  - [n.d.] (Folder 1.1)
  - 1941 (Folder 1.2)
  - 1942 January-March (Folder 1.3)
  - 1942 April (Folder 1.4)
  - 1942 May-July (Folder 1.5)
  - 1942 September-October (Folder 1.6)
  - 1942 November-December (Folder 1.7)
  - 1943 (Folder 1.8)
  - 1944 January-July (Folder 1.9)
  - 1944 August-December (Folder 1.10)
  - 1945 (Folder 1.11)
  - 1946 January-June (Folder 1.12)
  - 1947 January-1948 May (Folder 1.13)
  - 1957-1969 (Folder 1.14)
- Series II. Typescripts: The Significance of Art: Foundations of an Aestheics of Value
  - Copy 1, circa 1944 (Box 2)
  - Copy 2, circa 1944 (Box 3)
  - Copy 3, circa 1944 (Box 4)
  - Copy 4, circa 1944; [pp. 1-187] (Folder 5.1)
  - Copy 4, circa 1944; [pp. 188-429] (Folder 5.2)